jordan wirfs-brock

website: jordanwb.com twitter: @jordanwb linkedin: bit.ly/JWBlinkedin

nutshell

Jordan is a PhD student in Information Science. Her research focuses on how unexpected mechanisms—sound, taste, participatory experiences—can help people understand quantitative data. She has over ten years of professional experiences as a journalist, data analyst, producer, program manager and designer focused making complex information approachable.

education

University of Colorado

Boulder, CO PhD student in Information Science - GPA: 4.0/4.0 Began August 2017

University of Colorado

Boulder, CO MA in Newsgathering - GPA: 3.949/4.0 May 2011

Graduate Certificate in Environment, Policy and Society

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Cambridge, MA SB in Aeronautic and Astronautic Engineering - GPA: 4.5/5.0

May 2006 Minor in Literature

work experience

Mozilla Remote Research Associate Fall 2018

Employ user experience research methods (surveys, interviews, user studies, etc.) to understand listening cultures and help develop emerging technologies around listening

Oath/Yahoo Sunnyvale, CA Summer 2018 User Experience Research Intern

Conducted research to support Yahoo products and explore future product areas; used a range of methods (interviews, user tests, eye-tracking, diary study, focus groups, surveys)

Inside Energy / Rocky Mountain PBS

Denver, CO Data Journalist 2014 - 2017

Produced stories for web, radio and TV about the energy industry; experimented with creative techniques like stop-motion animation and data sonification; collaborated with a team of reporters on investigative projects; performed at live events; practiced audience-driven storytelling; established data-driven culture for a start-up media organization

The Piton Foundation Denver, CO

Data Curator; Product Manager 2011 - 2013

Analyzed socioeconomic data and community indicators; co-founded Floodlight, a tool for digital storytelling; grant-writing, product/technology development, outreach and community training

Center for Environmental Journalism, University of Colorado Boulder, CO Graduate Research Assistant 2008 - 2010

Assistant to Ted Scripps Fellowship; coordinated weekly seminar speakers; maintained program website

Kwangju Foreign School Gwangju, Korea High School Teacher; Princeton In Asia fellow 2006 - 2007

Taught Biology, Physics, Pre-Calculus, Model U.N., Modern World History, Health/PE; coached cross-country, basketball; advisor for yearbook + art-lit magazine

training + teaching	Society of Professional Journalists/Google Newslab Trainer Teach hands-on workshops in technology, mapping, data visualization, immersive media and more at newsrooms and classrooms	2017 - 2018	
	Designing and Leading Hands-On Workshops		
	SRCCON - "Let's create a roadmap for user testing and feedback in newsrooms"	2017	
	SRCCON - "Can we pair program the news?"	2016	
	SRCCON - "Data audioization workshop"	2015	
	Society of Professional Journalists Denver Workshop - Introductory Data Skills	2016	
speaking	TEDxMileHighWomen - "Your Relationship With Energy Is Broken. Let's Fix It."	2016	
spearining.	Computer Assisted Reporting Conference - "30 Energy Data Story Ideas in 60 Minutes"	2016	
	The Aspen Challenge, Denver	2014	
	Colorado Library Consortium Spring Workshops Keynote	2014	
	Obama for America Colorado Citizen Engagement Roundtable, Ignite Session	2013	
	Knight Media Learning Seminar	2013	
	National Neighborhood Indicators Partnership Meeting	2011, 2012	
	Denver Regional Council of Governments Regional Data Summit	2012, 2013	
	Western Arts Federation Symposium	2012	
awards	2019 Tangible, Embedded and Embodied Interactions (TEI) student design competition concept/design - "Quantuition"	, best	
	2018 International Conference on Auditory Display ThinkTank graduate consortium participant - "Conversational Sonification" 2018 Heartland Regional Emmy Nominee, informational series - Explaining fracking in 3 videos 2017 University of Colorado Data Visualization Contest, 1st place - "Indian Lands and Fossil Fuel Resources" 2017 Public Radio News Directors Incorporated Award, 1st place independent podcast - Out There, "High on Failure" 2017 Heartland Regional Emmy Nominee, informational short - "What Does The Clean Power Plan Mean For You?" 2016 Illinois Humanities People-Powered Publishing Fellow - Project: Reciprocal Podcasting 2016 National Headliner Award, 2nd place radio series - "Blackout"		
	2016 Regional Murrow, investigative radio - "Abandoned Wells" (data journalist supporti Stephanie Joyce)	ata journalist supporting reporter	
	2015 National Headliner Award, 2nd place radio feature - "How You're Invested In Oil An journalist supporting reporter Dan Boyce)	d Gas" (data	
skills	Data and Relational Databases / Excel, SQL, Python (with pandas and Jupyter notebooks) Mapping + GIS / ArcGIS software, Google Fusion Tables, TileMill, Carto		
	Web Design + Programming / JavaScript, HTML, CSS, GitHub		
	Data Design / Illustrator, Tableau, d3.js		
	Chamitallian / Audia adition madeat madeation animation vide at a stantillian		

Storytelling / Audio editing, podcast production, animation, video storytelling

interests Trail and Ultra-Running / Seven-time 100-mile run finisher; 48-hour, 72-hour and 10-day races; member of Girls Heart Rockets, a space and science-themed all-women relay team Writing / essays, poetry, fiction

Home brewer + craft beer enthusiast

Drawing / sketch-notes, comics, illustrations

MIT Varsity Athletics / basketball, cross-country, outdoor track